（2004年11月19日）
（在NBA的比賽中 球員與球迷之間發生一起事件）
（原始影片不對外公開）
[評論員]華萊士被犯規了，華萊士被—噢！華萊士！
[commentator] And Wallace is fouled. And Wallace is-- Oh! Wallace!
狠推了阿泰斯特一把
Right on Artest!
這可能演變成嚴重事件
This has potentially serious…
（給我底特律，其餘免談）
[droning stops]
NBA別再假裝了
[man over radio] It's time for the NBA to stop pretending.
應該改名TBA
Call it the TBA, the Thug Basketball Association.
叫暴徒籃球協會
這些自大的球員向來不必守規矩
These guys never had to follow the rules. They are prima donna athletes.
想不到會發生這種事
I couldn't believe what was going on.
那場鬥毆太經典了
It was an iconic brawl.
好不專業
Unprofessional.
完全不專業
Absolutely unprofessional.
[droning continues]
美國近郊人士很難理解
It's hard to explain to people from suburban America.
羅恩亞泰斯特的理智線斷了
Ron Artest just went nuts.
他真的有心理問題
He does have psychological problems.
我們有難同當， 兄弟！
We ride together, fam!
一定要嚴懲史蒂芬傑克遜
Stephen Jackson deserved the most severe penalty.
我以後再也不談這件事 把這句話錄下來好嗎？
I'm never talking about this shit again. Can you get that on camera
我當時受不了這種壓力
It was way too much pressure for me. Way--
我拼命想逃脫，找到出口
I felt I was trying to escape, to find any way to escape.
外界對NBA施壓，要他們導正風氣
Pressure on the NBAto clean up its ranks,
昭告大眾，他們不是暴徒
send a message that these guys are not a bunch of thugs.
要是知道來龍去脈
If you actually knew what happened,
知道這對大家的影響…
you actually knew the effects that it had on everybody…
[tense music playing]
你根本不會問這件事
…you wouldn't even be asking questions.
我想公佈真相 究竟怎麼回事？一格一格看清楚
I want the story out there. What happened Go frame by frame.
[tense music continues]
公佈完整影片
[O'Neal] Show people all the footage.
真相浮出水面後，你再自己下結論
Then when it's told, you make your own conclusion on what it is.
（奧本山宮殿）
[cold electronic music playing]
["Your Sweet Love" by Lee Hazlewood plays]
NETFLIX 原創紀錄片系列
Stranger's arms reach out
To me
'Cause they know
I'm so lonely
Then my mind goes back
To you
And your sweet love
Sees me through
-[song fades] -[insects chirping]
[heavy breaths]
（劇名：NBA 球場鬥毆事件）
[static crackling]
[tense music playing]
[crowd booing and yelling angrily]
[indistinct yelling]
好，我沒事，我自己能走！
All right, all right, all right, I'm good. I can walk!
-好，沒問題 -我自己能走！
-Okay, fine. -I can walk!
好，放開
Okay, all right.
我們有難同當， 兄弟！
We ride together, fam!
[indistinct yelling]
[indistinct]
一到更衣室我就坐下
[O'Neal] Once we got to the locker room, I remember just sitting down,
呆坐了一會，然後…
and I sat there for a while, and I sat…
我穿著制服坐著
I literally sat in my uniform.
手機震動個不停
And my phone just vibrating. Like, it's going off.
老婆、我媽、我哥、朋友全打給我
My wife calling me, my mother, my brother, friends calling me.
收到超過一百則簡訊
I think I had over a hundred text messages.
我現在還是很激動
My adrenaline's still pumping.
我坐著，努力讓自己鎮靜
I'm just sitting there trying to calm down, man.
還在鬥毆模式
Just trying to calm down. I'm still in fight mode.
我心裡想著：”你完了”
In my head, I'm like, "You're done."
“可能不能再打球了 開始另謀出路吧”
"There's no way-- you might not ever play again."
"Start thinking about something else."
謝謝，感激不盡
[siren wailing]
擔架抬走了一名受傷的球迷
Thanks, I appreciate it.
[reporter] A stretcher taking away an injured fan.
現場有一輛閃著警示燈的救護車 裡面載著受害者
An ambulance on the scene with flashing lights and victims inside.
活塞隊和溜馬隊在奧本山宮殿的比賽
This is what became of the Pistons-Pacers game
演變成這樣的結果
at the Palace of Auburn Hills.
但大家都說這是底特律的醜事
But everyone's saying it's a black eye for Detroit
把矛頭指向某些特定溜馬隊球員
and pointing the finger at some particular Pacers players.
我到家之後
[O'Neal] When I got home,
通宵看這支影片
I'm up all night looking at this.
我們以為運動場要定特殊規則
[newswoman] We think there have to be special rules in these sports arenas,
也必須謹慎對待
and we think we have to have kid gloves and treat these zillion-dollar athletes
天價球員，好像他們是天之驕子一樣
as if they're different and special.
太多聯盟球員的…
Too many players in this league
行為和態度證明 他們的心態和暴徒無異
whose actions and attitudes bespeak kind of a thug mentality.
我邊看電視
[O'Neal] I just remember watching TV,
邊想著身為職業球員 我付出多少心血
and now I'm thinking about all the work that I put in as a pro player
才能擁有當時的成就
to get to the point I've gotten to.
我所有的付出
Everything you worked for,
瞬間化為烏有
in a split moment. [snaps fingers]
（歐尼爾）
我從南卡羅萊納州哥倫比亞市的 險惡環境中長大
Getting out of my position of how I grew up
in Columbia, South Carolina
讓我養成不同的人生觀
put me in a position to look at life differently.
州議會大廈之前還掛邦聯旗
They flew the Confederate flag on the state house
一直到三、四年前才拿下來
until as recently as three or four years ago.
[somber music playing]
因為有這樣的環境 我從小就必須做決定
You make decisions growing up because your environment is that.
環境限制了你的發展
Your environment states that's what you should be doing,
但籃球成了我的避風港
but basketball became that safe haven for me
所以我不像許多人一樣誤入歧途
to, you know, not go down the road that many do.
[somber music continues]
星期三即將舉辦全國籃球協會選秀會
The National Basketball Association draft of new talent is coming up on Wednesday.
今年的選手相當年輕
This year's crop is younger than ever.
一名高三生自認已經能進NBA
[newsman] One high school senior, Jermaine O'Neal,
thinks he's ready to play in the NBA.
傑曼歐尼爾！
[announcer] Jermaine O'Neal!
歐尼爾，來自南卡羅萊納的全美球員
[newsman] O'Neal, an All-American from South Carolina,
決定要到選秀會碰碰運氣
has decided to try his luck in the draft.
我知道進NBA的時機已經成熟
[O'Neal] I knew it was time to make the jump to the NBA.
我可以改變家族血統
I'm the piece that can change the bloodline of my family,
粉碎世代承襲的
that can break the chains of things
厄運鎖鏈，我就是關鍵的棋子
that have been going on over and over and over and over again.
I'm that piece.
[somber music continues]
波特蘭拓荒者隊選中南卡羅萊納州
The Portland Trail Blazers select Jermaine O'Neal
歐克萊爾中學的曼歐尼爾
from Eau Claire High School in South Carolina.
[crowd cheering]
我17歲被選進波特蘭拓荒者隊
[O'Neal] I got drafted at 17, picked to the Portland Trail Blazers.
有機會能打球
[cheering]
[O'Neal] You get an opportunity to play something
這是許多人17歲的夢想
that many people just dream about doing at 17.
對吧？那是開始開車的年紀
Right Just started driving.
但我也記得那些噓聲
But I also remember the boos.
[crowd booing]
那是我很強的動力來源
That was one of the things that really motivated me.
大家都不看好我
Because people were counting me out.
現在，傑曼歐尼爾…
[commentator] And now Jermaine O'Neal…
我打的第一場NBA球賽
[O'Neal] I remember the first time I played in an NBA game.
我彷彿置身夢中
It's like living a dream.
上場打NBA球賽的感覺超夢幻
There ain't nothing like walking into those NBA arenas.
感受到那股能量
Feeling that energy.
敵隊的恨意
[crowd cheering]
-That hate if you're opposing team. -[boos]
或是主隊所享受到的熱情
Or that incredible love if you're home team.
傑曼歐尼爾！
-[crowd cheering] -[commentator] Jermaine O'Neal!
當時我是最年輕的NBA球員
I became the youngest player at the time to play an NBA game.
我現在要從中學最頂尖的場上球員
Now I'm going from beingthe best player on the court in high school
變成自己球隊同位置的第四名球員
to being the fourth-best person at my position on my own team.
我從沒想過不打球，完全沒有
You never think about not playing. You just don't think about that.
這麼想就輸了
Because if you do, you're a loser.
但我會想：“你怎麼不給我機會？”
But it was like, "Damn, how dare you just not even give me a chance"
我含淚坐在長椅的一端
I remember sitting at the end of the bench and tears in my eyes.
我心想：“我一定要做些改變”
I was like, "Something gotta change."
[static crackling]
溜馬隊兩個月前才輸給歐尼爾的球隊
Well, it was just a couple months ago when the Pacers lost to an O'Neal,
這週他們卻換到了傑曼歐尼爾
but this week, they gained one in JermaineO'Neal.
我接到電話 說我從波特蘭被換到印第安納時
When I got the callthat I got traded from Portland to Indiana,
我很興奮 這是我和雷吉米勒當隊友的好機會
I was so excited. It was an opportunity to play with Reggie Miller.
雷吉！
[chanting] Reggie! Reggie!Reggie!
我是雷吉的鐵粉
I'm a die-hard Reggie fan.
我來為雷吉加油
I'm here for Reggie. [laughs]
我特地來看雷吉比賽
I come to the games because of Reggie. [chuckles]
我知道他絕不服輸，是傳奇人物
[O'Neal] I know he's a true competitor. He's a legend.
我告訴他們 “我的衣物櫃要在他的隔壁”
I told them, "Look, put me right next to his locker.
“我要和他說話”
I need to talk to him."
雷吉出手，命中得分！
[commentator] Here's Reggie. Here's the shot!
Ah!
[cheering]
我為印第安納溜馬隊效力18年
[Miller] I played 18 years for the Indiana Pacers.
籃球等同印第安納的空氣
Indiana breathes basketball.
這是他們的生命
They live it.
所以，身為籃球迷的我
So, me being a basketball junkie,
宛如置身天堂
I was in heaven.
我很幸運，唐尼沃爾許
And I was fortunate that Donnie Walsh,
也就是總裁兼總經理，冒險延攬我
the president/general manager, took a chance on me.
雷吉把印第安納溜馬隊…
Reggie was the guy that really put the Indiana Pacers
（印第安納溜馬隊總裁 唐尼沃爾許）
帶到前所未有的道路
on a trajectory they had not been on before.
他真心想贏球
He really wanted to win
比所有人更努力爭奪冠軍
and did more than anybody anywhere in attempting to get the championship.
我們邀請到 印第安納溜馬隊的雷吉米勒
Reggie Miller of the Indiana Pacers is here.
他是相當偉大的NBA球員
He is oneof the great basketball players in the NBA.
-歡迎來到本節目 -很高興能上這個節目
-Great to have you. Thanks for coming. -Thank you. My pleasure.
上一季的光榮戰績 會不會對你在本季造成壓力？
Is there more pressure on you this season because of the success of last season
應該會
[Miller] I think so. Um…
我想奪冠
I-I wanna win the championship.
這是我的重要目標 去年我們與冠軍擦身而過
That is… That is my big goal. We came very close last year.
（2000年NBA總決賽）
打入2000年總決賽，卻輸給湖人隊
[Miller] We got to the finals in 2000, and we lost to the Lakers.
傑克遜想突破俠客的封鎖投藍
[commentator] Jackson looking to throw it in against Shaq.
雷吉轉身投籃…
Reggie turns and puts it up.
碰到籃框 把湖人隊送上NBA冠軍寶座
Off the rim, and the Lakers are the NBA champions.
我們忍不住要問
[newsman] We can't help but wonder, how many more chances
球技非凡的雷吉米勒還有幾次機會？
for the magnificent Reggie Miller
我打了14年，從沒奪冠過
[Miller] That was my 14th year, and we had never won a championship.
看著所有的合約，想到我的年齡
Looking at all the contracts and the age, it was time for us to get younger,
是該注入新血的時候了
所以他們找來傑曼來當對策
and they made and pulled the plug in getting Jermaine.
我被交易的第一天
[O'Neal] The first day when I got traded,
當時我在印第安納波利斯的 一家運動餐廳
I was at Champps, downtown Indianapolis.
一走進去就聽到 “我們就是拿戴爾戴維斯來交換他”
And I walked in, I heard, "That's the guy we traded Dale Davis for."
大家超不爽
People were pissed.
他們毀了這支球隊
They gutted the team.
當時我20歲
I was 20 years old.
我從沒有當過先發
I've never been in a position to be a starter
一晚都沒有
every single night,
但我願意犧牲一切
but I'm willing to sacrifice every single thing I got
換取這個機會
for this opportunity.
我打包票，你們不會失望
100% certain that you guys won't be disappointed at all.
你們對這項交易會很滿意
I think you'll be very, very happy the trade was made.
我的貢獻會很大
I can bring a lot to the table.
傑曼非常投入，努力證明
I think Jermaine was really dedicated
他是聯盟裡的頂尖球員
to trying to prove he was one of the best players in the league.
在場外也很有自信
And he handled himself off the court with that kind of confidence.
NBA要的就是這種人
You know, he was kinda what the NBA wanted.
我後來慢慢覺得
I was kinda thinking, not right away, but down the road,
他有一天也許能取代雷吉
maybe he could replace Reggie.
他展現了能成為明星球員的徵兆
[Miller] He's definitely showing signs he'd carry this franchise,
我指的不是他的戰績
and what I mean by that is not the numbers he does,
而是他能領導隊上年輕球員
but I think the leadership he brings to a lot of the younger guys in here.
你必須比別人更拚，一定要夠狠
You have to outwork people. Like, you just gotta be a savage.
當時我覺得傑曼是很奇特的球員
[Walsh] Jermaine, to me, was a very unusual player for then.
他能擔當重責大任
He can do a lot of big man things,
也能在別人運球時搶球 很有運動細胞
but he can also take people off the dribble,
and he was very athletic.
歐尼爾漂亮的旋轉一圈 繞過弗拉德迪瓦茨，好厲害！
[commentator] O'Neal with a gorgeous 360 spin on Vlade Divac. Wow!
-[crowd cheers] -[whistle blows]
傑曼就快成為比賽的超級球星
[Miller] Jermaine was on the verge of becoming a superstar in our game.
漸漸成為印第安納溜馬隊的門面
And he was becoming the face of the Indiana Pacers.
（從男孩蛻變成男人）
NBA全明星中鋒 是首次獲選的傑曼歐尼爾
[announcer] First-time NBA All-Star center Jermaine O'Neal.
[crowd cheering]
後來我覺得：“好，我喜歡”
Then I'm like, "Okay, I like it."
我不在乎上場時間或得分
I didn't care about minutes or points.
我要這些年輕人來當主力
I wanted all these young guys to do the bulk of the work.
我要為印第安納拿到冠軍
I wanted to win a championship for Indiana.
當時我一心追求這個目標
That's what it was all about for me.
[buzzer sounds]
[crowd cheering]
我的主要焦點
My main focus,
不必在一年內達成
and it doesn't always take place in one year,
就是讓球員之間合作無間
is get players that fit with each other.
[inaudible]
（亞泰斯特）
（溜馬隊、公牛隊 成功互換七名球員）
我被換到印第安納後 坐巴士去邁阿密比賽
[Artest] When I got traded to Indiana, I was on the bus going to the Miami game.
他們說：“別下巴士”
They said, "Don't get off the bus."
“你被交易了”
Uh, "You're traded."
我根本不甩他們，我下了巴士
And I remember…
You know, I never listen. So, I got off the bus.
他們說：“別上場”
And they said, "Don't get on the court."
結果我上場了
And I went on the court.
他們說：“快下場”
[chuckles]
And they said, "Get off the court."
我說：“不要“，然後練球一小時
I said, "No," and I practiced for an hour.
他們今天第一次 和印第安納波利斯的媒體見面
[newsman] In their first meeting with the Indianapolis media today,
印第安納溜馬隊最新的隊員
the newest members of the Indiana Pacers
表示離開芝加哥，讓他鬆了一口氣
expressed relief over getting out of Chicago.
很高興來到這裡 在芝加哥打輸了兩年
[Artest] It feels good to be here after a couple of years in Chicago losing,
打得很辛苦 我希望能為奪冠出一份力
and, uh, it just was hard, you know. I just wanna bring that winning effort.
我的經歷
I didn't have a lot of trust with people
讓我不太信任旁人
just because of things that I was going through and stuff.
我永遠把所有人看做敵人
For me, it's enemies. Everybody's an enemy to me, all the time.
但只要一上場，我會信任隊友
But once we step on the court, I trust that.
記得交易後第一次練球
[Miller] I remember the very first practice after the trade.
那次練了三小時
That practice, which was three hours,
傑曼走向我
I remember Jermaine coming up to me and was like,
他說：“我好像沒練得這麼辛苦過”
"I don't know if we've ever practiced this hard."
我回：“沒錯，但這是好事”
And I'm like, "You're right. I think this is gonna be good."
羅恩也許是我見過最認真的球員
[O'Neal] Ron was probably the hardest worker
that I've ever seen in my life.
他也許是我們十年來
I think he was probably the most talented defensive player
見過天分最高的防守球員
that we saw in an entire decade.
羅恩很不一樣
Ron is different.
不一樣不是壞事
But different isn't bad.
代表有時也很獨特
Different is just sometimes unique.
羅恩的天分很獨特
And Ron was unique in his talents.
[crowd cheering]
我沒見過誰打球像他這麼拚
[Walsh] I'd never seen anybody play as hard as he did.
他是場上的一股力量
He was a force out there.
-[whistle blows] -[crowd] Oh!
我一上場就全心投入
When I step onto the court, I'm just 100% in.
放馬過來
Bring it to this. Bring it to this. Bring it to this.
儘管考驗我，天王老子我都不怕
Test me right here, it don't matter who. You could be the biggest gangster.
這是我們的戰場，我願意死在球場
This is where we go. I'll die here.
[inaudible]
每支球隊都需要羅恩亞泰斯特這種人
[Miller] Every team needs a Ron Artest.
需要大家都有點忌憚的人
You need a guy that everyone's a little bit afraid of.
被亞泰斯特撞出界
[commentator] Hammered out of bounds by Artest.
現在和熱火隊助理教練凱斯艾斯金斯 吵了起來
Now having words with Heat assistant coach Keith Askins.
Wrong guy to pick with is Artest.
千萬別惹亞泰斯特
[whistle blows]
他就是這樣
You know, that's, uh, that's who he is.
球技很高超，但脾氣要控制一下
Hell of a player, but he's gotta get that under control.
他總對我說：“這樣不公平 他們無權這麼做”
He would say to me,
"Well, that's not fair. They shouldn't be able to do that."
我才發現他過度膨脹正義感
I realized he's got an exaggerated idea of justice.
當時我討厭所有人，總是在生氣
I just didn't like people. I always had a chip.
當時我們有傑曼 這個最佳內線防守員
At the time, we had the best interior defender in Jermaine,
還有羅恩這個最佳外圍防守員
and we had the best perimeter defender in Ron.
[propulsive music playing]
[crowd cheering]
兩人在場上合作無間
It was poetry in motion at times when they were on the court.
如果你突破我的防守，傑曼會來守你
After I shut you down, if you do beat me, then Jermaine will shut you down.
傑曼和我也都是火爆小子
We were also loose cannons mentally. Yeah, me and Jermaine.
傑曼個性火爆，但他很能自製
Jermaine's a loose cannon, but he kept it really tight.
[whistle blowing]
我們的心態很相似
[O'Neal] We had a lot of the same mentalities.
頑強、不妥協，一定會修理你
Dog, hard-nosed, we gonna go get you.
[crowd cheering]
我們連戰皆捷
[whistle blows]
And we just kinda started blazing through teams.
印第安納溜馬隊打得相當漂亮
The Indiana Pacers, they are rolling.
印第安納溜馬隊戰績是NBA之冠
The Indiana Pacers have the best record in the NBA.
印第安納溜馬隊是聯盟最強球隊
[newsman] Indiana Pacers, best team in the league.
印第安納溜馬隊目前打遍東區無敵手
[newsman 2] Indiana Pacers, the team to beat in the East right now.
你們不懂我們當時有多強
You guys don't understand how good we were.
[crowd cheering]
我們蟬聯聯盟最佳戰績一整年
[O'Neal] We had the best record in the league the whole year.
打進了東區聯盟總決賽
Made it to the Eastern Conference Finals.
回想起來，就是那場季後賽引爆了…
I look back at it now, and that was the series that ignited…
一切
everything.
底特律隊中人才濟濟
Detroit had incredible talent,
我們都知道這會是場硬仗
and we knew it was gonna be a tough scenario.
我們是最強的兩支球隊
[Miller] We were the two best teams, defensively and offensively.
攻防都是頂尖
所以我知道 打贏了這場，等於拿到冠軍
So I knew whoever won this was gonna win a championship.
[crowd cheers]
[whistle blows]
[crowd cheering]
那場季後賽逼出我們的極限
That series, they pushed us to the limit.
[tense music plays]
[whistle blows]
籃球季後賽
In playoff basketball,
不容許重大失誤
the margin of error is thissmall.
大家體能都很好，是…
Everyone has the physical capabilities. It's…
[tense music continues]
這次漢彌頓被撞了
[commentator 1] Whoa! Hamilton is fouled this time.
[crowd booing]
亞泰斯特也許會被判驅逐出場 但這絕對是故意犯規
[commentator 2] Artest may be thrown out of the game,
but it's definitely gonna be a flagrant.
這招太不明智
[commentator 1] That's just not a good move.
這對他們很重要
[commentator 2] This is a huge play for them.
比賽打到這個時間，務必保持冷靜
At this time in the game, you can't lose your cool.
實在太重要了
It's just too crucial.
不能在錯誤的時機撞人
You can't foul at the wrong time
讓對手佔上風
-and give your opponent an advantage. -[buzzer sounds]
14年來頭一次
[commentator] And for the first time in 14 years,
活塞隊打進NBA總決賽！
the Pistons go to the NBA Finals!
他們拿下2004年東區聯盟冠軍！
They're the 2004 Eastern Conference champions!
我們在底特律輸了第六場比賽
We lost game six in Detroit.
感覺就像被人捅了一刀
[somber music plays]
It's like somebody sticking a knife into you.
羅恩亞泰斯特故意犯規
The flagrant foul
that took place with Ron Artest, was that the difference in this game
這是勝負關鍵嗎？
絕對有影響
Well, it certainly had an impact.
這實在很難說
You know, it was a tough call.
（我只是舉起前臂而已）
Yeah, I just put my forearm up, you know what I'm saying And, um…
而且…
我覺得…
I think, uh…
但裁判看到了，他…
But the ref saw it.
在東區聯盟輸給底特律
You know, he was, uh…
Losing to Detroit in the Conference, I remember.
我們本來能打進總決賽，本來贏定了
Yeah. We should've went to the finals. We should've definitely won.
（混亂收場）
[somber music playing]
（故意犯規又進攻拙劣 溜馬隊本季到此為止）
（亞泰斯特故意犯規成為頭痛問題）
（亞泰斯特總無法冷靜）
那場季後賽，我們輸了 冠軍是哪一隊？
When we lose that series, who wins the championship
底特律活塞隊震撼了洛杉磯湖人隊
[commentator] The Detroit Pistons have just shocked the Los Angeles Lakers.
[crowd cheering]
他們心理素質比我們強
They were mentally tougher than we were.
我心想：“你們看吧！”
I'm like, "You guys!"
[tense droning builds]
真讓人洩氣
It was just frustrating.
-[droning fades] -[birds chirping]
再見
[Artest] See you later. Love you.
愛妳
離垃圾遠一點！
Get out the garbage!
我隔年就知道有問題
The next year, I knew something was wrong, like…
我知道有很大的問題 我需要冷靜一下
I knew something was definitely wrong and that I just needed to step back.
我說：“我要拿退休申請書”
I said, "I want my retirement papers,"
溜馬隊 說：“不行，你必須打球”
and the Pacers said, "No, you gotta play." [chuckles]
“你的合約還有六年”
"You're under contract six more years." [chuckles]
我覺得羅恩每天都會語出驚人
I felt like Ronnie was coming out with something like that every day.
他總說：“我明天不能練球 我要玩音樂”
One day he'd say,
"I can't come to practice tomorrow. I gotta do my music."
我有權利做我想做的事
As a man, you gotta be able to do what you want.
如果我不想打球了
So if I decide to wanna leave the game or take a month off, I'm a grown man.
或是想休一個月的假…我是成人了
做自己想做的事並不瘋狂
It doesn't make me crazy, you know, to wanna do something I wanna do.
如果是在年初請假…
If you're asking for time off at the beginning of the year…
大哥，球季還有六個半月， 你現在要請假？
I mean, dude, we got six and a half months left,
and you're asking for a timeout now
我的唱片會再 11月23日發行
I still got my album coming out November 23rd,
唱片發行後，我會…
and after the album comes out, I'm gonna, uh,
保證全心全意準備奪冠
you know, make sure all my time is focused on winning the championship.
我總是非常焦慮
I had so much anxiety all the time.
[tense music playing]
心跳很快
You get that heart pumping.
當時我控制不了，每天都這樣
It was something I couldn't control at that time. It was every day. Every day.
[tense music continues]
我心想：“我真的要努力找出癥結點”
So, I was like,"I really do need to try to figure out what's wrong."
“為甚麼籃球和隊友無法讓我開心？”
"Why are you not happy around basketball and your teammates"
“為甚麼我不開心？一定要找出來”
"Why are you not happy Figure it out, figure it out."
我當時已經接受治療 但改善需要時間
I was already in therapy, but you don't get better overnight.
我們知道他比賽時有心理醫師隨行
You know, we knew he had a psychiatrist that… that traveled everywhere we went.
也知道他要接受她的治療
We knew he had sessions that he had to have with her.
我們只知道這麼多
We knew that much,
但我們根本沒聽說過
but we were never, ever, you know, told that he had a certain issue,
他有醫療問題
我有躁鬱症
medical issue.
I had depression and anxiety.
對某些事感到憂鬱，對未來感到焦慮
I would be depressed about certain things and have anxiety about future things.
有些人能控制情緒，我做不到
Some people have control over their emotions. I don't.
如果我感到興奮、開心 蓋別人火鍋、贏球
If really I'm excited, happy, I've just dunked on somebody, game-winner,
那種激動的程度對我不好
that emotional level is not a good place for me.
無法控制情緒的起伏
Positively or negatively, you have no control of that.
冷靜點！你在搞什麼？
Come on! The fuck you all doing
我不吃你這一套！夠了，兄弟！
I'm not gonna do this with you! Come on, my nigga!
快去叫保全！
Get your motherfucking security right!
場內有人鬥毆
[man] We got a fight back here.
你要冷靜點
[man 2] You gotta chill.
羅恩有時急躁了點
At times, Ron could be a little edgy.
傑曼和羅恩的互動也讓人不安
And the dynamic between Jermaine and Ron was unsettling.
我覺得壓垮我們的最後一根稻草
I think the final straw for us
就是他聲稱家裡有喪事
was when he said he had a death in his family
卻跑去參加嘻哈雜誌獎
and went to the Source Awards.
各位來賓，掌聲歡迎
[announcer] Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the Tru Warier
真勇士的羅恩亞泰斯特和派帝帕洛！
Ron Artest and Petey Pablo!
你說要去奔喪，結果三四天後
You were saying you were going away for a funeral,
then three or four days later,
我們打開電視 看到你在頒獎典禮頒獎
we turn the TV on and you're presenting an award at an award show,
我們卻三、四天沒看到你
and we ain't seen you in three or four days.
得獎的是…我不知道上來幹嘛 但沒關係
And the winner is…
I don't know what I'm doing up here. It's all good though.
我大概是想逃避
I felt I was trying to escape.
我絕對是想找個出口
I was trying to find any way to escape. Definitely.
我不會再回答關於羅恩的問題
I'm not gonna answer any more questions about Ron.
羅恩不想來，那他就不重要
Ron doesn't wanna be here. Ron doesn't matter anymore.
溜馬隊才重要 每天穿上球衣的球員才重要
It's about the Pacers, the players that suit up every single day.
我不想再回答關於羅恩的問題
I'm tired ofanswering questions about Ron.
我懇求這些人
I'm pleading with these guys.
“大家要同心！”
"Get on the same page!"
我無法讓他們瞭解這個大好機會
I could not get them to understand the opportunity.
我從不聽雷吉的話
[Artest] I never listened to Reggie.
每次他想領導或教導我
So any time he's, like, giving me leadership andmentorship,
我就想：“練習時再痛宰他”
I'm thinking, "Bust his ass in practice."
我知道我們集合了
I know that we're putting together
可能會惹毛彼此的年輕球員
young guys who could rub each other wrong,
但當時我奪冠心切
but, you know, I really wanted to win,
也在幫隊上找最後的關鍵球員
and I was looking for one final piece of the team.
所以我才交易史蒂芬
And that's why I made the trade for Stephen.
（傑克遜）
我接到唐尼沃爾許和大鳥博多 打來的電話
[Jackson] I remember getting that call from Donnie Walsh and Larry Bird.
我在街上，手機只好開擴音
I had to put 'em on speakerphone 'cause I'm on the block.
我和朋友在第3200街
I'm on 3200 with all my homeboys.
"Welcome to the Indiana Pacers," duh-duh-duh.
“歡迎加入印第安納溜馬隊“之類的
[indistinct]
那時我很開心
You know, it was a great moment.
當他說：“歡迎…” 我的朋友全高興得跳起來，覺得…
When he said, "Welcome to…" all my homeboys get to running.
我知道這是難得的機會
Just, "Oh!"
And I knew the opportunity was… was priceless.
史蒂芬的加入
[Miller] When Stephen came,
對我們是最棒的事 因為我們有了傑曼和羅恩
it was the best thing for us, because now we got Jermaine, Ron,
現在又多了超強的瘋漢 史蒂芬傑克遜
and now you're bringing in another tough, somewhat crazy dude in Stephen Jackson.
大家都知道，打贏印第安納才有勝算
Everything has to come through Indiana. There's no secret.
他們想要達到目標，就要打敗我們
They gotta come through us to get to where they wanna be.
我覺得我們是最強的球隊
And I-I-I think we're the team to beat.
我們有超強球員 只要好好調度就行了
We have all the pieces. We gotta put 'em together.
你很享受挑戰
[reporter] A challenge you relish.
我準備好接受挑戰 這是我的人生目標
Yeah. I'm ready for a challenge. That's what I live for.
我抗壓性強，這是我的長處
-I make love to pressure. -[laughs]
我和他都是混街頭長大的
That's what I do.
Me and him was, like, we both kinda street.
所以會爭著防守頂尖對手
So we're arguing about who's gonna guard the best guy,
簡直快打起來
like, almost come to blows.
後來我會說“好吧，史蒂夫，讓給你”
Then I'm like, "All right, Steve, you got it."
我心裡會想：“這傢夥好誇張！“ ”
So I'm like, "This guy is crazy!" [laughs]
我們共通點很多，但個性截然不同
We got a lot of similarities, but we're totally different.
我知道他有點不對勁
I knew he was a little off. You know what I mean
但他是很傑出的籃球選手
But he was a hell of a basketball player.
我只看這一點，其他的我不在乎
And that's all… I didn't judge nothing else but that.
我也很怪，也很任性，整天呼麻
I didn't care. I was weird. I did my own thing. I smoked weed all day.
我和羅恩這種人，把籃球當命一樣
Guys like me and Ron, we look at basketball as our life.
上帝給了我這種天賦 讓我幫助家裡脫貧
This is all we can do. God gave me this gift to help my family,
to getout of the situation I was in.
傑克個性很積極，我們個性很相像
[O'Neal] Jack is a very aggressive person. We have a lot of similar traits.
他行動很積極快速，你能清楚感受到
He would turn that volume up very quickly and tell you about it.
他求勝心切
He's down for the cause.
我的特點就是忠誠 認定你之後，就絕不改變
I'm a loyal guy. Like, one thing about it. If I'm with you, I'm with you, you know.
打完球後，我們去酒吧 要是有人說了什麼
We shoot this, and we go to a bar afterwards, somebody say something,
我會第一個站起來 我的個性就是這樣
I'll be the first one to stand up. That's how I am.
認定你之後，就絕不改變 我就是最後的關鍵
If I'm with you, I'm with you.
I was the missing piece.
他們當時是這樣說的
That's basically what they were saying.
我我是球隊奪冠的最後關鍵
I was the missing piece to the championship team.
只有少數球隊能說
[Miller] There's only a handful of teams that can say,
“我們有機會奪冠” 在我18年的籃壇生涯中
"We have a shot to win the championship."
Out of my 18 years,
那一季，我們有條件奪冠
that season, we were loaded for bear.
那年我們意氣風發
This was our year.
我們等待這場對決已久
[commentator] This is the Showdown of the East we've been waiting for.
早在賽季開始前，這場競爭就在醞釀
A rivalry that's been brewing long before this season ever started.
（印第安納對底特律）
Two teams, similar styles, only one survivor.
兩支球隊，風格相似 只有一隊能勝出
[uneasy music playing]
（奧本山宮殿）
去奧宮比賽時，我們已經七勝兩敗
[Artest] Going into the Palace, we was already seven and two.
我超級想打這場比賽
I knew that was the game I wanted more than any game.
卻不知道會發生甚麼事
But I didn't know what was gonna actually happen.
我們是去立威的
We were coming in there to make a statement.
“你們拿過冠軍
"Yeah, y'all got the chip, but we're letting y'all know
但聽清楚
今年我們贏定了”
y'all gonna be seeing us this year."
-我們來自哪裡？ -底特律！
-Where we from -[all] Detroit!
底特律是最難打球的地方之一 那裏的球迷很強悍
Detroit was one of the hardest places to play.
They don't make it easy for you.
[crowd cheering]
Whoo! Yeah!
Yeah!
進去…進去奧宮時
Obviously, um, you know, we're facing a tough challenge
我們早知道要打一場硬仗
going into a… uh, going into the Palace.
他們的球迷族群很激進
They have a rabid fan base.
很死忠，很熱情
Very faithful and admiring fans.
有時很愛鬧
Um, and very boisterous at times.
讚！第一名…！讚啦！這樣就對了！
Yeah! Number one, baby! Number one!
Yeah! That's what I'm talking about!
球迷常常是贏球的關鍵
The fans were a huge part of a lot of the success,
因為就算在場上 還是聽得到球迷熱情的歡呼
because even though you're on the court, you can hear those fans going crazy.
我們到體育場時，就知道活塞隊會贏
When we would come into the gym, we knew the Pistons were gonna win.
只是不知道贏幾分
We just didn't know by how much.
[tense music playing]
只要讓兩萬個人 聚在一起四、五個小時
Any time you put 20,000 people together for four or five hours,
而且他們還喝酒
and they're drinking,
條件都具備了，隨時都可能出問題
the stage is set.
Somewhere, somebody's gonna have an issue.
我們本來打算撤銷兩個人的季票
There was a couple of guys that we were gonna remove their season tickets.
我們受夠他們胡鬧了
We kinda had enough of their, uh, shenanigans.
當時是週五晚上，我們週六不必上班
It was a Friday night. We didn't have to work Saturday,
讓人感覺更開心
so it was kinda like, you know, you kind of enjoyed it more.
想個喝幾杯
Have a few drinks, hang out with friends. Kinda like treating myself.
和朋友出去玩，犒賞自己
查理是球迷，他有季票
Charlie's a fan. Uh, he was a season ticket holder.
當晚他有闖禍
And he had issues that night. And so, we were…
我們本來…打算告訴
我們那晚要收回他的季票
going to address it with him that we were taking away his season tickets that night.
我們通常每個月 會辦兩、三場活塞隊的比賽
We would normally probably work the Pistons games
two, three times a month.
那天我們被派到東區
On that day, we were assigned on the east side.
我們大概也對印地安那也有些敵意
I think we had some rivalry with Indiana, I think, as well,
球迷很興奮
and the crowds were pretty charged up.
NBA所有球員都想拿到這個
Everybody in the NBA wants one of these.
他們比賽就是為了這個：冠軍戒
This is what they play for, a championship ring.
我到場為體育頻道轉播球賽
[Gray] I was there to broadcast the game for ESPN.
印第安納是非常優秀的球隊
Indiana was a terrific team.
他們想爭奪冠軍
They were championship contenders
可能也是當時NBA最強的球隊
and may have, at that time, been the best team in the NBA.
但底特律隊也很出色
But Detroit was a good team.
他們是很棒的球隊
[tense music playing]
They were a really good team.
[tense music continues]
我的手指斷了，所以打了石膏 改由史蒂芬當得分後衛
[Miller] I had broke my finger, so I was in a cast.
Stephen was moved to the shooting guard.
我不知道自己踏進了 敵意這麼強烈的地方
I didn't know the magnitude of the rivalry that I was walking into.
去年一整年，他們在東區聯盟總決賽
You gotta thing, they was wrestling with this team all last year
全力對付這一隊，準備爭得你死我活
in the Eastern Conference Finals, about to go to blows.
這絕對是我們宣揚戰力的一仗
It was absolutely a statement game for us.
毫無疑問，這是屬於我們的時刻
This is our moment, and let's leave no doubt.
他們覺得那是屬於他們的一年
[Wallace] They felt that was their year,
我們想要捍衛寶座
and we felt like we had to defend our title.
那晚奧宮氣氛很激昂
I remember that night. The Palace was electrifying.
感覺就像靈魂出竅一樣
Man, it was…
It was almost like having an out-of-body experience.
讓人覺得汗毛直豎
You could feel the hair stand up on the back of your neck.
[tense music continues]
每次參加全國轉播的球賽
[Donaghy] Whenever you go into a nationally televised game,
體育館中的喧鬧聲就不一樣 電燈更多，攝影機也更多
there's a different roar in the arena.
There's more lights. There's more cameras.
他們指派評審非常謹慎
You know, they're real careful who gets assigned games like that
不想讓聯盟丟臉
because they want not to be embarrassed as a league.
當時大家都不喜歡 當活塞隊比賽的裁判
Nobody liked refereeing the Pistons back then.
那晚鐵定不輕鬆
You knew you were in for a rough night.
有班華勒斯、史蒂芬傑克遜 和羅恩亞泰斯特
When you have Ben Wallace, Stephen Jackson, Ron Artest,
想不出事都難
I mean, that's just a recipe for disaster right there.
[crowd cheering]
來自密西根州的超棒籃球迷
Basketball fans from around the great state of Michigan,
和從世界各地來到奧宮的各位
and those of you here at the Palace from across the world,
各位請注意
stay on your feet.
讓我們熱烈歡迎
-["The Final Countdown" playing] -Time to meet and greet the ballers
代表底…特律活塞隊的球員！
representing the D… troit Pistons!
那場比賽的播音員超有活力
[O'Neal] They had the most dynamic announcer. Right
當你聽到：“底特律今天要吃癟了” 會讓人熱血沸騰
And it gasses you, where you saying, "Look, I'm at your ass today, Detroit."
身高206公分 背上繡了紅色三號的中鋒
[announcer] At 6'9", the center, wearing the big red three,
班…華勒斯！
B-B-B-B-B-B-B-B-B-Ben [trills lips] Wallace!
他們介紹班華勒斯出場
I remember they did the Ben Wallace introduction. That got me hyped.
讓我超興奮 心想：“痛宰他們一頓吧，等著瞧”
That got me hyped. Like, "Let's bust they ass. Fuck that."
[crowd cheering]
當時我不知道班華勒斯的哥哥剛去世
At the time, I didn't know Ben Wallace lost his brother.
擁有那股能量，真的…
Having that energy, you know, it was…
我知道自己只能 把那股能量發洩在籃球上
[inhales]
I knew I couldn't put that energy nowhere else but into basketball.
當時簡直和火藥桶沒兩樣
It was like a powder keg.
這是正規賽季期間相當精采的一戰
[commentator 1] A fun matchup to watch during the regular season.
只希望兩隊在季後賽還能再次對決
We can only hope they'll meet again in the playoffs.
活塞隊的主場表現目前都很完美 奧宮再次人滿為患
Pistons so far perfect at home. Another packed house at the Palace.
進入比賽會場時
Going into that game, I thought we could beat Detroit,
我們自認能擊敗底特律
我希望這種球隊能獲勝
and I wanted to see if this type of team would work.
[commentator 1 continues indistinctly]
[tense music playing]
歐尼爾
[commentator 2]O'Neal.
亞泰斯特後退… 羅恩亞泰斯特這節打得真漂亮
[commentator 1] Artest steps back… Oh, what a quarter for Ron Artest.
十分之四…
Four-tenths of a…
就算我情緒不穩，我的球技還是很好
Even though at that time I was struggling, I was playing great.
比賽根本一面倒 我們從頭到尾都稱霸球場
The game was a beatdown. We dominated from beginning to end.
羅恩如入無人之境，沒人擋得了他
-Ron dominated. Nobody couldn't stop him. -[whistle blows]
當時四個人都擋不了羅恩
Two, three, four guards couldn't guard Ron at the time.
他身手太敏捷 絕對是場上的最佳球員
He was too agile. He was definitely the best player on the court.
我們領先兩位數，這些孩子在閒聊
We were up double digits, and my young boys were jawing.
他們合作無間
They were clicking.
羅恩和傑曼兩人
Ron and Jermaine.
羅恩表現很好，傑曼也是
It's good Ron, and it's good Jermaine.
表現得太精彩了
It was fantastic.
[tense music continues]
這是屬於我們的時刻 是我們的揚名立萬的時機
This is our moment. It's our coming-out party.
我們大搖大擺地走進球場
We came in with a different type of swag.
史蒂芬打得相當好
Stephen's like… he's so clutch.
我心想：“這傢夥大放異彩”
I'm like, "Wow, this guy makes every big shot."
"Wow."
[commentator speaking indistinctly]
我們馬上知道我們是最棒的球隊
We knew right away we was the best team.
殺得對手毫無招架之力
We were kicking their ass.
很明顯，他們組成了一支冠軍球隊
They put a championship team together. It was obvious.
[tense music continues]
因為我們痛宰對手
'Cause we were beating them down,
正常的觀眾都走了
the normal ticket holders were gone.
早就離開了
They had left.
所以三三兩兩往下移動的觀眾
So it was the people that were trickling their way down
走到前排位子時，早就喝醉了
that were probably already liquored up, coming on down to fill those seats.
他們的行為很失禮，球賽都快結束了
Oh, man, very disrespectful, like, the way they did it.
竟然派先發球員上場
The game was almost over. They had starters out there playing.
他們領先15、20分
They were up by 15, 20 points.
華勒斯阻擋得真漂亮！
[commentator] Oh! Wallace with a terrific block!
那不算犯規
That's not a foul.
比賽最後，我們領先15分 我認為比賽已經結束
At the end of the game, we're up by 15. In my mind, the game's over.
賈馬爾汀斯利告訴羅恩
Jamaal Tinsley tells Ron,
“現在你想犯規就犯規吧” 羅恩看著他說：“啊？”
"You can get your foul now." Ron looked at him like, "Huh"
“現在你想犯規就犯規吧”
"You can get your foul now."
現在你想犯規就犯規吧，你可以走了 好嗎？
You got your foul. You can go now, right All right
你幹嘛對他這樣講？
Why are you even telling him that
羅恩夠火爆了，不用搧風點火
Ron doesn't need a battery in his back to do something crazy.
亞泰斯特拿下24分，歐尼爾20分
[commentator] Artest with 24, O'Neal at 20,
克羅希爾15分，汀斯利 13分
Croshere 15, Tinsley 13.
回防時，我守班，他們傳球給他
[Jackson] As we're running back, I guard Ben.
我不想緊守著他，也根本不想犯規
When they throw him the ball, I'm not gonna try to play defense on him.
I'm not even gonna try to foul him.
他帶球上籃
-[Artest] He was going for a layup. -[commentator] Oh!
我不要他上籃得分，就推了他一把
I didn't want him to get the layup, so I pushed him.
比賽到那個時間點，這樣犯規太嚴重
It was too hard of a foul at that point in time during the game.
-[whistle blowing] -[crowd cheers]
天哪，華勒斯！直接揍了亞泰斯特！
[commentator] Oh, Wallace! Right atArtest!
如果不把他們拉開 後果可能不堪設想
This has potential to be serious if they don't get between them.
華勒斯超不爽 兩隊球員試著把雙方拉開
Wallace upset. Players trying to hold each other off.
史蒂芬傑克遜和華勒斯想當和事佬
Stephen Jackson, and we see Wallace trying to be peacemaker.
傑克遜在大喊…
Now Jackson yelling…
我對吵架沒有意見
[Miller] The dust-up I have no problem with.
這很司空見慣，推人或撞人
That happens all the time. The pushing, the shoving…
都是假的
You know, that's all fake.
NBA球員通常不想打架
Most of the time, nobody in the NBA wanna fight.
出拳攻擊是很失禮的行為
It has to be real disrespectful shit for somebody to throw punches.
[commentator] …in here to get him away.
[indistinct yelling]
事情的引爆點
Where it all turned
就在羅恩去計分台躺下的時候
is when Ron went and laid on the scorer's table.
[indistinct yelling]
[tense music playing]
他走去躺下來，這很反常
Went over and laid down, which is not normal.
躺在計分臺上是很反常的舉動
It's not normal to lay down on the scorer's table.
也很扯
That's crazy, too, you know
簡直比犯規更糟糕
That's… That's… That's almost worse than the foul.
[indistinct yelling and commotion]
當時我已經在治療中 所以我馬上做練習
[Artest] I was already in therapy. So I was practicing in real time.
其中一個方法是數到五
One thing was take five, right
要是有甚麼事 我會默念：“一，二，三…”
So if something happens, you're like, "One, two, three…"
做出任何反應前先數數字 就有比較多的時間思考
Before you do anything, just count, 'cause then you get more time to think.
[indistinct yelling]
隊友把我團團圍住
[Artest] My team was all around me.
感覺很好玩，好像我是大人物一樣
It was funny 'cause I felt like I was a big dog, like…
我的確覺得隊友變得…我瞭解隊友
I did feel like my team got…
I know my team,
知道傑曼不會讓班對我動手
so I know, like, Jermaine's not gonna just let Ben come over and touch me.
這點我確信，我有史蒂夫傑克遜
I know that for a fact. Like, I got Steve Jackson.
我心想：“好，我甚麼都不用做”
I'm like, "All right, Cool. I don't need to do nothing. I'm fine."
“我沒事”
[indistinct yelling]
華勒斯還是很激動
[commentator] Wallace is still charged up.
我猜想華勒斯被判驅逐出場
Now, Wallace, I would assume, has been ejected.
班戴了一堆臂環、頭帶和護腕
Ben wore, like, 10,000 armbands and headbands and wrist bands,
他開始丟東西
and he started throwing things.
[crowd clamoring]
我看到他丟頭帶和護腕
[Donaghy] Saw him throwing the headband and the wristbands.
顯然生氣了
He definitely was losing his temper.
[inaudible]
球迷不知道多數球員彼此都是好友
The fans don't know the majority of us are actually friends,
以為這真是是街頭鬥毆的場面
so they think that this is a real street brawl scenario.
所以，球迷的反應會和球員一樣
So however you react, they're gonna react.
你做出這種行為 你以為球迷會怎麼做？
If you do this, what do you think they gonna do
球員讓群眾更陷入瘋狂
The crowd feeds off the players.
從我的眼角
Out of the corner of my eye,
我瞄到它飛過來
I see it coming.
超級慢動作
Super slo-mo. Like, it just…
感覺就像…
大家應該都看得到，速度就是這麼慢
It just… Everybody was supposed to see it. That's how slow it went.
[disturbing droning]
擊中！
[Miller] Bam!
亞泰斯特跳過計分台
[commentator] Now Artest has jumped over the scorer's table
想往長椅衝過去！
and is trying to get down to the bench!
亞泰斯特衝到看臺！
Artest is in the stands!
場面太亂了，連球迷都捲進來
Oh, this is awful. Fans are getting involved.
看到他衝過去，我馬上也衝過去
Once I saw him go, I went.
他需要幫手
He needed aid.
我衝去時，另一杯啤酒砸到他的臉 就是那個男的…
As I get to him, another beer is thrown in his face. And that's the guy I…
史蒂芬傑克遜和球迷打成一團
[commentator] Stephen Jackson's in the fans.
保全拼命想恢復秩序
The security trying to somehow restore order.
球迷和球員打起來了！ 球員努力互相幫忙！
Fans and players are going at it! The players trying to help each other out!
拉席德華勒斯衝向看臺！
Rasheed Wallace going into the stands!
[crowd clamoring]
好丟臉
[commentator] This is a disgrace.
[disturbing droning continues]
球員都跳進來互相幫忙
All the players, they're jumping in there to try and get the other players out
因為球迷捲入鬥毆了
because the fans have become involved.
[all yelling]
奧宮的這個場面真令人難過
[commentator] Oh, what a sad scene here at the Palace.
走下看臺時，我心想：“沒事的”
[Artest] Walking down the stands, I'm thinking, "It's good."
沒想到結果不是這樣
I didn't think anything else was gonna happen at all.
我以為爭吵會結束
I thought it was gonna be over.
我停下來看
[O'Neal] I just stopped and paused, and I just started looking.
“保全在哪裡？”
"Where is the security at"
現場沒有員警，大樓裡沒看到員警
There was no police. I didn't see a policeman in the building.
我沒看到保全，沒人來阻止這場鬥毆
I didn't see any security. There was nobody there to stop this.
到處都是人，真像一場大亂鬥
Everybody was everywhere. I mean, it was just like a melee.
他們把我們推往出口
And then, they were pushing us towards the exit.
不知怎麼地，我到了球場上
Somehow, I got on the court.
我很震驚，像是看到外星人
I remember being shocked, like I'd seen an alien, like…
“這傢夥到球場來打架？”
"This guy, uh, coming to the court to fight"
當時我受不了了，極力避免打架
'Cause at that point, I'm fed up.
但這些人給了我理由 這是我的舒適圈
I'm trying not to fight, but these guys are giving me a reason…
羅恩亞泰斯特衝進看臺後 正常人不會走到球場上
This is my comfort zone.
You wouldn't in your right mind walk down on the court and think it's a good idea
覺得應該要和他單挑
to take on Ron Artest after he's been in the stands.
奧宮的這個場面真令人難過
[crowd yelling]
[commentator] Oh, what a sad scene here at the Palace.
活塞隊的長椅前方爆發另一場鬥毆
[crowd yelling]
[commentator] Now another fight's breaking out
in front of the Pistons bench.
是一名球迷，真是太危險了
It's a fan.
This is very, very dangerous.
球迷們在丟…
Fans are throwing…
[crowd yelling]
[tense music playing]
我沒看到他過來 那個王八蛋揍了我一拳
I didn't see him coming at all. Sucker punched me.
真是…
You know, quite a…
很賤的舉動
bitch move, tell you the truth.
我全速衝刺過去想幫他
I just all-out sprint over there to try to help him.
[crowd yelling]
好在他滑倒了
[Miller] He slipped. Thank God.
這是傑曼籃壇生涯中最棒的失誤
It was the best miss of Jermaine's career.
[tense music continues]
如果傑曼那拳命中的話…
'Cause if Jemaine would've connected on that punch…
[crowd yelling]
那名球迷必死無疑
…that fan would have been dead.
現在回到球場
[commentator] …now onto the court.
羅恩亞泰斯特的眼神非常可怕
[crowd yelling]
Ron Artest has a look in his eye that's very scary right now.
最可怕的一刻 就是我發現場面多失控
The scariest moment wasonce I realized how out of control this got
情勢可能會有多糟的時候
and how much further it's gonna go.
911，您好
快派人來奧宮
-我們確實有人在場 -有人在打架
-球員間在打架？ -快點！
好，員警確實正在路上
拜託快一點
[distant siren wails]
當時球場上有三名警員
At the time, we had three officers on the court.
對付兩萬個人，可以說勝算渺茫
Not the best odds against 20,000 people.
場面失控了
It was out of control.
於是我們決定把球員拉離球場
That's why the decision was we need to get the players off the court.
把他們拉離球場之後 球迷就會冷靜下來
If we get them off the court, the fans will calm down.
[tense music continues]
一名警員從我身後跑過來
[Miller] An officer runs up from behind me,
他拿出了噴霧劑
and he has his mace thing out,
準備要噴羅恩
and he's getting ready to mace Ron.
[all yelling]
我並不想噴羅恩亞泰斯特 他已經躺在地板上了
I had no intention of spraying RonArtest. He was already down on the floor.
他早就…他很疲憊的樣子
He had… He looked wore out.
我碰見穿西裝的雷吉米勒
At some point, I ran across Reggie Miller in a suit.
當時我不認識雷吉米勒或任何球員
And I… At the time, I didn't know he was Reggie Miller or a player
他穿著西裝，所以我問他在幹甚麼
'cause he was in a suit. I'm asking him what is he doing.
你竟然不認識 印第安納溜馬隊的雷吉米勒？
How you not know Reggie Miller's on the Indiana Pacers
[tense music continues]
[inaudible]
我抓住那名警員 我問：“你在幹甚麼？”
[Miller] I grabbed the officer. Like, "What are you doing"
我說：“把球迷都趕出球場，別噴他”
I was like, "Go get all these people off the court. Don't be macing him."
[yelling indistinctly]
那時我徹底被惹毛了
That's when I really got pissed off.
你們不想幫我們 我們十五個人要對三萬個人
Like, y'all are not trying to help us. It's really 15 against 30,000.
他們想叫溜馬隊回到更衣室
[commentator] They're trying to get the Pacers to go back to the locker room.
[crowd yelling]
大家抓住羅恩，開始離場
[Miller] We all grab Ron, and we start to run.
人潮全湧進同一區
[O'Neal] You see everybody merge to one area.
他們手邊有甚麼就丟甚麼
And they throwing everything they can get their hands on.
[crowd yelling]
[tense music continues]
[music intensifies]
失控的球迷想攻擊球員，他們丟…
[commentator] Now these ridiculous fans trying to go at the players and throwing…
一不小心就會傷到人
[crowd yelling]
[commentator] Somebody could really get hurt.
[angry yelling]
活塞隊球迷做了很壞的示範
[commentator] This is a bad showing from the Pistons fans.
從樓梯上丟瓶子下來
Just firing bottles from the stairs.
好，我沒事
All right, I'm good.
-我自己能走！ -好！
-I can walk! I can walk! -Okay!
我們有難同當， 兄弟！
We ride together, fam!
[indistinct yelling]
我對攝影機說：“我們有難同當”
I remember saying to the camera, "We ride together."
我們永遠有難同當 這是我的態度
We gonna always ride together. That was my attitude.
我很開心幫了我兄弟
I was happy that I helped my brother down.
很開心能夠幫兄弟一把
I was happy I was able to come to my brother's aid.
從我在更衣室的表情就看得出來
You can see that in my face in the locker room.
我很滿意我們的舉動 為兄弟兩肋插刀，太棒了！
I was happy with what we did. I was there for my brother. Yes!
-先生，請問你叫甚麼名字？ -查理哈達
-[reporter] Tell me your name, sir. -Charlie Haddad.
他打了我的臉，現在還很痛 我整臉都要照X光
He hit me in the face. I'm still hurt. I need X-rays on my whole face.
我根本不知道發生甚麼事
I don't even know what's going on.
別說了
You gotta stop, you gotta stop.
-到外面再說 -不准待在這裡
[man] Take it outside. You can't be in here.
我被打之後，我們從不同的房間離場
After I get hit, we left and went through a different room,
好像是保護我們一樣
like they were protecting me.
他們開始把人帶到我的辦公室
They started bringing people into my office.
有兩個人說：“有人打傷自己的話
A couple of them were like, "This would be funny
就能告他們 事情一定會很好玩”
if one of us, you know, hurt ourselves and we can sue."
[sirens wailing]
[tense music continues]
我看著現場
I remember looking. I see people rocking chairs, trying to get the chairs loose.
看到有人在搖椅子，想把椅子搖鬆
[crowd yelling indistinctly]
體育館內的人向我們包圍
The arena closed in on us very quick.
人群逐漸失控
The crowd was getting a little bit, um, out of control.
我的武器可能兩三下就被搶走
Somebody easily could grab your weapon.
[crowd yelling]
突然間，我看到椅子在空中飛
[O'Neal] Then, all of a sudden, I saw the chair up in the air.
[crowd yelling]
球迷想傷害我和其他人
People were trying to hurt me and others.
場面非常可怕
It was just a horrible, horrible scene.
[crowd yelling]
[tense music continues]
[booing]
[indistinct yelling]
[somber music playing]
我們往更衣室走，很慢但很穩當
[Miller] We get to the locker room, and slowly but surely,
大家開始加入自己的說法
everyone was starting to filter in with their own stories.
我心裡一直在想 “傑曼一定會給我好看”
The whole time, I'm like, "Jermaine is gonna kick my butt."
我一直這麼想
The whole time.
我不想看到他
I didn't wanna see him.
我知道他會超不爽 傑曼滿腦子都想贏球
I knew he was gonna be pissed. It's all about winning for Jermaine.
羅恩…靠過來問我 “我們惹禍上身了嗎？”
Ron, uh, leans over to me and asks me, "Are we gonna get in trouble"
我問：“甚麼意思？”
Said, "What you mean"
我怒火中燒
I just lost it.
他衝向羅恩，我們拉開他們兩個
He charged Ron, and we end up breaking it up.
[indistinct yelling]
我需要確認事情已經結束
I just needed confirmation that it was kinda, like, over.
真的
Yeah.
後來警方想把我抓去坐牢
Then the police comes in and trying to grab me to take me to jail.
我還…不過，我還在求生模式
And I'm still… Again, I'm on survival mode.
我說：“我不會跟你們走”
I'm like, "Look, I'm not going with you."
“我要坐巴士去搭飛機”
"I am getting on this bus and getting on that plane,
我要回家找律師”
and I'm going home."
"Reach out to my lawyers."
NBA和部分球迷 昨晚引發前所未有的混亂
[static crackles]
The NBA and some of its fans achieved a new level of outrageousness last night.
溜馬隊和球迷在看臺爆發鬥毆
A fight broke out between the Pacer team and the fans in the stands.
溜馬隊和活塞隊的底特律之戰 發生可恥的打架事件
…disgraceful brawl at the Pacers-Pistons game in Detroit
這也許是美國運動史上 最難看的純暴力行為
may be the ugliest act of pure hooliganism in US sports history.
各方都在討論這件事 體育頻道每5分鐘就放一次影片
Everybody talked about it. Every show talked about it.
ESPN played it every five minutes.
底特律週五晚上不是在打架 根本就是在暴動
It wasn't a brawl in Detroit Friday night. It was a full-scale riot
這是我國史上，球迷和球員間
and one of the ugliest incidents of player-fan violence
最醜惡的暴力事件
we've ever seen in this country.
球員拿了天價酬勞
The players, paid gazillions of dollars here,
這些人從來不必守規矩
these are guys who have never had to follow the rules.
他們違反了職業運動的第一條規則
They violated the number-one rule for any professional athlete,
那就是，不管聽到甚麼話 被甚麼東西砸到
and that is no matter what is said, no matter what is thrown at you,
絕不能衝進看臺
you don't go into the stands.
評論風向改變了
The narrative had changed.
矛頭全指向球員
It was all about us, the players.
全是羅恩、史蒂夫和傑曼的錯 他們是無禮的暴徒
Ron, Steve, JO, it's their fault. They were being thugs, acting out of line.
突然間，我的個性有問題
Like, all of a sudden, my character
is in question.
重點不只是多少人批評
It wasn'tjust the amount of people that were saying it.
還包括批評者的道德高度
It was the stature of the people who were saying it.
無庸置疑地
And it's tough to argue the certain thug mentality hasn't crept into basketball.
某些暴徒的心態還沒滲透到籃壇
聯盟的暴徒形象，需要有人加以剔除
The thug image is there until somebody excises it from the league.
“這些暴徒”，他用的就是這個字眼
"These are thugs." Literally, that's the word that he used.
其他人都同意 “對，問題就是饒舌音樂…”
Everybody else signing off. "Yeah, it's rap music…"
曲棍球互毆幾十年
Well, they're not saying that
他們卻沒這樣講
when hockey is beating the hell out of each other for decades.
NBA表示正在洗刷不良少年的形象
The NBA says it's fighting a bad boy image.
他們有刺青，愛打架，吸毒被抓
The tattoos, the fights, the drug busts.
媒體要幫NBA 推動這種愛爭吵的嘻哈運動嗎？
Are the media helping the NBA market this as a kind of in-your-face, hip-hop sport
和前一代的魔術強森及喬丹相比
The hip-hop generation of players
seeming to some more estranged from the fans
嘻哈世代的球員似乎比較疏遠球迷
than the Magics and the Michaels that preceded them.
協會馬上頒布服裝規定
The dress code was immediate.
（NBA總裁制訂服裝規定）
（史騰捍衛NBA服裝規定）
有一句古諺說：“黑鬼有錢準沒好事”
It's the old famous saying. "Should have never gave them niggas no money."
部分當代知名球員引發眾怒
There is real resentment against some of today's major players.
很多球迷覺得他們薪資過高
Many of the fans consider them to be overpaid,
表現太差，嬌生慣養又不成熟
underperforming, overly coddled, and immature.
在很多情況下，球員還沒學會
Players have not learned how to… how to act, in many cases,
在正常的文明世界該有的舉止
within a civilized, normal society.
電視對聯盟施壓，要他們說
Television was putting pressure on our league to say, "Hey, look,
“這些人就是流氓”
these guys are… are hoodlums, these guys are out of control,
“這些人失控了，他們問題多多”
these guys are this and that."
全世界都看到了
The visual of NBA players going into the stands and fighting
NBA球員衝向看臺鬥毆的畫面 我們要立刻阻止才行
goes around the world. You have to stop that immediately.
多年來，NBA受到龐大壓力
The NBA has been under heat for a number of years
球員形象不佳一直嚴重傷害NBA
and clearly has been hurt
by this impression a lot of its players give
外界認為他們只想當流氓
that they are, uh, gangster wannabes
在少數的情況下，真的是重犯
or, in some few cases, actual felons.
NBA承受導正風氣的壓力
Pressure on the NBA to clean up its ranks,
昭告大眾，他們不是暴徒
send a message that these guys are not a bunch of thugs.
聯盟會怎麼做，很令人好奇
It's going to be real interesting to see what the league does.
他們無法承受這樣的惡名
This is the type of publicity they can't afford.
你不覺得NBA必須昭告大眾…
Don't you think it's important the NBA has to send a message…
-已經昭告大眾了 -強烈地昭告…
-A message will be sent. -…send the strongest…
-大眾… -確保不會再有這種事
-…possible message… -…to make sure it doesn't happen again.
（鬥毆後48小時）
[indistinct chattering]
現在宣佈下列人士禁賽…
Today, I announce the, uh, following suspensions,
（NBA總裁 大衛史騰）
uh, resulting from the actions
起因是在11月19日 溜馬隊對活塞隊的比賽中
at the Indiana Pacers and Detroit Pistons game
所發生的行為
on November 19th.
[inhales deeply]
印第安納的羅恩亞泰斯特 本季其他賽事禁賽
Uh, Indiana's RonArtest has been suspended for the remainder of the season.
[somber music playing]
印第安納的史蒂芬傑克遜禁賽30場
Indiana's Stephen Jackson has been suspended for 30 games.
印第安納的傑曼歐尼爾禁賽25場
Indiana's Jermaine O'Neal has been suspended for 25 games.
針對上週五的籃球賽
The NBA has handed out unprecedented punishments
NBA對涉案球員做出史無前例的懲罰
to the playersinvolved in Friday night's basketball game.
約翰，這項懲罰也許前所未有
John, this may be unprecedented punishment.
NBA剛剛宣佈
The NBA just announcing
羅恩亞泰斯特本季其他賽事禁賽
that Ron Artest has been suspended
大衛史騰等於告訴大家、球員和球迷
for the rest of the season.
David Stern was basically telling everyone,
“類似事件下不為例”
players and fans alike,
"This will not be tolerated. An incident like this will not be tolerated again."
我絕對同意自己應該受罰
Not one time have I thought that I shouldn't be punished.
但禁賽25場？我不服氣 因為我的第一原則
But to 25 games I ain't okay with that, because everything I did,
是要保護自己
I had to do in protection.
要是事後馬上面談我就好了
I wish I could have been interviewed right after,
大家能討論是非對錯
'cause then people could have been like, "He's right," "He's wrong."
意見會比較多，但都是以影片為準
There could have been way more opinions, but the opinion was only on the film
我們被罰禁賽，也不能有意見
and the suspension, and we had to be quiet.
大衛史騰從沒和我聊過這件事
[O'Neal] I never had a conversation with David Stern about it.
大家的評論都是根據剪輯過的… 體育頻道的結論
The narrative was based on an edited…
conclusion on ESPN.
[somber music continues]
根本不是基於事實做出公平審判
Not even a fair trial of what it was.
史騰總裁對這件事掌有大權
Commissioner Stern has wide power in this situation, you know.
通常發生類似事件時
Usually, in light of situations where something like that occurs,
會引進獨立仲裁人
you have a situation where an independent arbitrator comes in
雙方會進行談判
and negotiates between the two sides
針對懲罰達成共識
to reach a… reach an agreement on some kind of punishment.
但因為事情發生在球場上
But since this was an on-court issue,
協力廠商仲裁人是…沒有協力廠商仲裁人
the third arbitrator is… There is no third arbitrator.
作主的是總裁大衛史騰
It is Commissioner David Stern. It comes to his doorstep.
這是他的權責，他說了算
大家會很想知道…
He's the final word.
-It'll be interesting to see… -Such a deal. I like that deal.
我喜歡這樣子，規則由你訂
You get to call the shots.
-也由你檢查 -對極了
-You get to review the shots. -Exactly.
亞泰斯特被判禁賽一整季 這是一致的決定嗎？
[reporter] The decision to suspend Artest for the entire season, was that unanimous
-沒錯 -為甚麼
-It was. -[reporter] Why
這是一致的決定
It was unanimous.
無異議通過
One-nothing.
感覺上，原本是很複雜的情況
[interviewer] It seemed at first, this was a complex situation,
突然變得很非黑即白
but then it suddenly became very black-and-white.
你覺得是甚麼改變了？
What do you think changed
你知道改變的原因吧？
-You know why it changed, right -[interviewer] Why did it change
說說看，為甚麼改變了？
-Do you know why it changed -[interviewer] No.
-你知道改變的原因吧？ -不知道
-你不知道改變的原因 -不知道
-You don't know why -[interviewer] I don't.
誰被判禁賽？
Who got the suspensions
-球員 -誰接管判決流程？
-[interviewer] Players. -Who took over this process
-史騰 -答對了
-[interviewer] Stern. -There you go.
NBA體認到不能讓球迷疏遠
The NBA is very cognizant of the fact that you don't wanna alienate any fans
因為他們是金主
because they're the ones that pay your bills.
他們想怪罪我們，拯救聯盟 不想怪球迷
They want to blame us to save the league.
They didn't wanna put it on the fans.
我看著大家找替死鬼
You're sitting, watching people throw darts.
[whooshing sounds]
卻甚麼也不能說
And you can't say nothing.
要是看了所有影片 大家的評論就會有些不同
I think the narrative is slightly different
if they see all the footage.
我不在意當替死鬼 但我也想公佈真相
I don't mind taking blame, but I also would like the story out there.
究竟怎麼回事？一格一格看清楚
Like, what happened Go frame by frame.
-[rewinding] -[tense music playing]
現在歡迎奧克蘭縣檢察官
I'd like to introduce David Gorcyca, the Oakland County prosecutor.
NBA擔心大家的觀感
[Gorcyca] The NBA was worried about their perception.
擔心形象遭到玷汙
Their image was… was tarnished,
他們做出很嚴厲的懲罰和禁賽判決
and the severity of the sanctions and suspensions was…
was pretty harsh.
他們希望我這些高薪惡霸發出信號
I think they wanted me to send a message to these millionaire-type bullies
說：“不能這樣做 ” 但我的職責是根據事實
that, "Hey, you can't be doing that."
But my job was to look at the facts
提出最適當的罪名
and decide what the appropriate charges are.
這場紛爭的涉案人士都要負相關責任
Everyone involved in this altercation will be held accountable,
不管是球員或球迷都一樣
regardless of their status as a player or a fan.
這個案件非同小可
The magnitude of this case was like no other.
媒體很令人厭煩
It got bothersome from a media perspective.
他們每天採訪我
They're just constantly on me daily.
對我的行事準則妄下斷言
They wanted to pontificate about what I should or shouldn't do.
辦這個案子很費力氣
It was a lot of work, uh, that went into this.
要花很久的時間調查
Gonna be a very long investigation,
也許比謀殺案更久 因為目擊證人太多
probably more complicated than a murder because we have so many witnesses.
警方報告超過一千頁
There was over a thousand pages of police reports.
和其他刑案不同 我們有各種角度拍的影片
Unlike most crimes, we had so much footage from different angles.
[intricate music playing]
奧宮體育館和大廳 每支攝影機的所有影帶
The Palace had a VHS tape for each and every camera that was inside the arena
都錄下了大家離場的畫面
and then all of the cameras that are on the concourse
我們想指認出每個人
as people were leaving.
We wanted to identify every single person--
球員、球迷、奧宮職員 要揪出所有犯案的人
player, fan, employee of the Palace.
Anybody that did anything wrong.
我們甚至
Eventually, we got to the point
把嫌犯的畫面全切割出來
where we isolated images of the people that we were looking for
開始對外散播
and we started broadcasting them out.
奧宮鬥毆事件出現突破性發展
[newswoman] Breaking developments in the Palace brawl.
本地第四台取得獨家影片
Local Four has obtained exclusive video
影片中的人被控在週五晚上的混戰中
of the man accused of throwing a chair into the crowd
把椅子丟向群眾
during Friday night's frantic melee.
丟椅子和攻擊兩名人士的人
The man who threw the chair
明確犯下惡意企圖傷害罪
and struck the two individuals was a clear-cut case of felonious assault.
有些球迷顯然很樂在其中
When you look at some of the fans, some of them relished it and got into it.
查理哈達和亞傑沙克佛德
Charlie Haddad and AJ Shackleford,
走下好幾排到球場上
they came down several rows and walked on the court,
其中一個走到球場上
one of them coming on the court
握緊拳頭和羅恩發生正面衝突
face-to-face with Ron with a clenched fist.
羅恩當時絕對有理由自衛
So Ron had every right to defend himself at that point.
太扯了，說得好像是我錯一樣
[Haddad] It was just crazy. Made it look like it was my fault.
完全不該這樣對待死忠球迷
They definitely did a very, very loyal fan wrong.
丟杯子的人就是我們想揪出的主嫌
[Gorcyca] One of the main people we wanted to locate was the guy that threw the cup.
我們要鎖定引發暴動的這個人
The main focushas to turn to the person who started the riot.
丟啤酒罐的人
The guy who threw a beer can.
最大的問題是 我們找不出丟杯子的人是誰
[Gorcyca] The biggest issuewas we could not identify the cup thrower.
我看影片時大喊：“再放一次”
And I was watching, and I went, "Play that back."
我看了10到12支影片才看清楚
It took me ten, twelve takes of the video to finally put it together.
我猛然想起自己在哪裡認識他
And it dawned on me where I recognized him from.
他是我鄰居的前男友
He used to date, uh, a neighbor.
我知道他是誰，親自找出丟杯子的人
So I knew who it was. So I ended up identifying the cup thrower myself.
-可以和你談談嗎？ -離開我家好嗎？
-[reporter] Can we talk to you -Can you leave our property, please
-我只是問能不能和你談談 -不能
-[reporter] Asking if I can talk to you. -[man] No, man.
疑似丟杯子的球迷
[newsman] The suspected cup-throwing fan,
檢方已經找出是約翰格林
who the prosecution identified as John Green,
他星期一想叫他的狗
tried to chase reporters away
把記者趕出他在底特律近郊的家
from his suburban Detroit home on Monday with his dog.
調度員打電話到辦公室找我
I was in my office and our dispatcher called back to me and said,
說：“電話中有人自稱是丟杯子的人”
"I have a guy on the phone saying he's John Green,
（約翰格林）
the guy that threw the cup."
（這樣不對，他們不該進看臺）
[Green] It was really wrong.
Those guys shouldn't come up like that into the stands.
而且還搞錯人
-Especially if you have the wrong guy. -[Martin] Right.
-其實是我 -是你？
-[Green] That's me. -[Martin] That's you
對，那裏，那是我
[Green] Yup. There, that's me.
這件球衣你還留著？
-[Martin] Do you still have this jersey -[Green] I have it.
-沒錯 -可以看看嗎？
-[Martin] Can I see it -[Green] Why
-幹嘛要看？ -我要確認…
-[Martin] I gotta verify that-- -[Green] I have it. Am I in trouble
我還留著，我惹禍了嗎？
沒有，目前沒人被控告
[Martin] No, no one's charged at this point.
先讓…先讓我打給律師一下
[Green] Before-- Let me call my attorney real quick.
他就是罪魁禍首
The man who started it all.
天哪，他成了頭號全民公敵
Boy, he became public enemy number one.
現在他首次發聲
Now, for the first time, he speaks out.
誰丟了杯子，很清楚
[Green] It's apparent who threw the cup.
你穿著…我看見班華…
[interviewer] You were wearing… I saw that Ben Wa--
站在那裏的如果不是你 就是你的同卵雙胞胎
Either that or you have an exact twin who was standing up there.
常有人對我這麼說
I've been told that a few times.
大家說你是丟杯子的人
[interviewer] Yeah. People have pointed at you as the person who threw that cup.
對
-[Green] Right. -[interviewer] When somebody says that,
你聽到這句話時
問杯子是不是你丟的，你怎麼回答？
"Were you the guy that threw the cup" how do you answer that
現在，我…我無可奉告
[Green] Uh, at this point, you know, I… No hable.
影片拍得很清楚
You know, I mean, the video pretty much speaks for itself.
羅恩亞泰斯特衝上去，經過你身邊 攻擊你旁邊的人
[interviewer] Did you feel bad at all when Ron Artest is flying up there
and goes right by you and attacks the guy next to you
當時你會過意不去嗎？
不會，我鬆了一口氣
[sighs] I felt relief.
好在！
No. [laughs] Jeez!
[laughs]
你會不會同情或憐憫
[interviewer] Do you have any, you know, compassion within yourself
那個替死鬼，因為你才是…
or some pity that he went after that guy, and you were the guy who…
我只後悔來不及把腳伸出來
The only thing I regret is not putting my foot out sooner.
-絆倒他嗎？ -沒錯
-[interviewer] And tripping him over -Yeah.
約翰格林是整個混戰的導火線
I think John Green precipitated this whole melee.
你好像覺得球迷才是罪魁…
[reporter] It seems that you're holding fans…
你覺得球迷的責任大於球員，對嗎？
You're saying fans are more culpable here than the players. Is that correct
我覺得有一位球迷責任比較重 那就是格林先生
I would say one fan is more culpable, and that being Mr. Green.
他若沒丟杯子 亞泰斯特也不會衝上看臺
He doesn't throw that cup, Artest doesn't go in the stands,
球員們也不會衝進看臺
the players don't go in the stands,
球迷們不會反擊看臺裡的球員
fans don't react to the players in the stands,
整場亂鬥也許在球場上就結束了
and probably the whole melee, uh, dies on the court.
除了約翰格林之外的所有人
All of 'em, except for, I think, John Green,
大家最後都
it was fines, costs, probation, community service
只被判罰錢、緩刑和做社區服務
that ultimately was the sentence of each one of 'em.
約翰格林因為丟杯子 被告一個人身傷害罪
John Green was charged with one count of assault and battery
因為打暈羅恩亞泰斯特
for throwing the beer,
as well as another count of assault and battery
被告另一個人身傷害罪
for coldcocking Ron Artest.
[indistinct courtroom chatter]
大家一定要瞭解，刑事訴訟結束後
[O'Neal] It's important for people to understand after the criminal part,
我對禁賽提起上訴
I went through a process to appeal my suspension.
聯邦法庭受理之後
And once it finally got to federal court,
聯邦法官看了所有角度拍的影帶
a federal judge, who then saw every camera angle,
說我的行為合情合理
said I had the right to do what I did.
老實說，我沒說謊
I'mma be honest with you. I didn't go up there with no story.
我根本不在乎
I didn't give a fuck.
我當時情勢所逼
I was put in a situation where I either help my brother or not help him.
我只能選擇幫或不幫我兄弟 我選擇幫他
我不該衝進看臺，我道歉 我不該讓聯盟蒙羞，我道歉
I chose to help him.
I apologized for going in the stands. I apologized for embarrassing the league.
所以我才離開 我才不要拍法官的馬屁
That's why I left it. I wasn't going in there kissing no ass.
我和傑曼的禁賽場數都沒減少
They didn't decrease mine. They decreased JO's.
羅恩一樣被判整年禁賽
And, uh, Ron had his full-year suspension as well.
審理期間很長
It was… [sighs]
a significant amount of time for what it was.
他們被判輕微人身傷害罪
They were misdemeanor assault and batteries.
通常整個流程花不到一小時
Normally, you'd spend less than an hour on that case, start to finish.
刑事司法系統對他們的判決
What the criminal justice system did to them
和NBA相比，根本是天壤之別
paled in comparison to what the NBA did to 'em.
那杯啤酒改變一切
That cup of beer changed everything.
讓所有人付出…
Cost all of us…
龐大的時間和金錢
a lot of money and time.
讓許多人付出慘痛代價
You know, it cost a lot of people a lot of things.
（5個月後）
[crowd cheering]
雷吉米勒受大家敬重
[commentator] Reggie Miller with universal respect.
今年表現很傑出 大家在討論他是否會重新考慮
And the way he played this year, there was talk about would he reconsider.
我們看不出雷吉有動搖的跡象
And Reggie's given no indication that this is anything but final.
雷吉！
[crowd chanting] Reggie! Reggie!Reggie!Reggie!
Reggie! Reggie!Reggie! Reggie!
Reggie! Reggie!Reggie!
發生這件事之後
[Miller] Once all this happened,
我心想：“退休的時候到了”
that's when I was like, "It's time for me to hang it up."
（謝謝你這十八季精采的表現！）
[crowd cheering]
如果沒有鬥毆事件，我們鐵定是冠軍
[Jackson] If the brawl hadn't happened, we would have been champions. No question.
這件事最叫人扼腕
That's the most fucked-up thing about it.
對於這個事件，我只遺憾
That's the only thing I regret about the whole situation,
無法實現諾言，和雷吉一起奪冠
is not being able to do what we said we was gonna do for Reggie.
我感覺苦樂參半
[somber music playing]
心中有錯綜複雜的感受
[Miller] It was bittersweet because so many emotions run through your mind.
18年的時光一閃而過
It was, like, fast forward 18 years.
這是我最後一場NBA球賽
That's your last NBA game ever.
感覺很特別
[voice breaking] It's special, man. It's pure and special.
純粹又特別l
真的
It is.
[crowd cheering]
這18年來
[voice breaking] For 18 years,
我真的很幸運
I've truly been blessed…
[crowd cheering]
能夠成為溜馬隊員和印第安納居民
…to be a Pacer and a Hoosier.
[crowd cheering]
對，很痛苦
Yeah, it's painful. Uh…
我覺得很痛苦，他付出了所有心血
For me, it's painful.
He did about everything you could do.
[somber music continues]
[crowd cheering]
我要說對不起，雷吉的家裡
I apologize for that,
不該連一枚冠軍戒都沒有
because there's no reason why, uh, Reggie,
uh, should be sitting home without a ring.
[crowd yelling angrily]
[yelling continues]
[sound cuts off]
我穿的印第安納球衣
[Artest] The Indiana jersey I had on
在我最慘的時刻出現在電視上
was projected on television at my worst moment.
穿上之後，我想躲起來
So, wearing it, I wanna hide.
[crowd yelling]
我再也不想穿印第安納的球衣打球 壓力太大了
I didn't wanna ever play in an Indiana jersey. Too much pressure.
我要求換隊 因為我沒有面對問題的勇氣
I asked to be traded, 'cause like I said, I don't confront things head-on.
大家分道揚鑣是最好的結果
But I think it'd be best if I move on, and then, you know, they can move on.
每個人各奔前程
You know, everybody can move on with their careers.
這是在打我的臉
[Jackson] That was a slap in my face.
經歷了前一年的苦難 現在你想離隊？
After allwe'd been through the last year, now you wanna leave us
這對我和羅恩有難以抹滅的影響
That had a lasting effect with me and Ron.
你要對受牽連的人負責
You gotta be accountable for the people that you pulled in.
我覺得那是我一輩子
And to me, that was the most coward scenario
見過最孬的一件事
I've ever fucking seen in my life.
有時你要承認自己是孬種 就這麼簡單
Sometimes you're a coward and you gotta admit it. Boom. Simple.
對，我是該…
You know, and, yeah, I didn't… I should've…
在那種時候，我是應該打給隊友
What you do in a moment like that is call your teammate,
別管雙方有多不自在
even if it's really uncomfortable.
我後悔沒這麼做
So, yeah, I wish that would have happened.
[somber music playing]
很久之後，我才明白我錯了
It took a long time to figure out what's wrong.
23歲時，如果我的人生更平衡 也許就能出人頭地
At 23 years old, if I had more balance, I probably would have been really great.
羅恩亞泰斯特，對了
Ron Artest, by the way, uh…
洛杉磯湖人隊羅恩亞泰斯特 今天宣佈重大消息
Ron Artest of the Los AngelesLakers had some big news today.
羅恩申請把法定名字改成“慈世平”
Ron actually filed papers to have his name legally changed to Metta World Peace.
好誇張，害我想到王子把名字
-Ridiculous. It reminds me of Prince… -So dumb.
改成“曾經叫叫做王子的藝人” 拜託！
…becoming the Artist Formerly Known as Prince.
鬥毆事件後
How long did that symbol last
我告訴治療師：“我只想達到平衡”
After the brawl, I told my therapist, "All I wanna do is have balance."
“其他的都不在乎”
"That's it. I don't care about nothing else."
我試著對球賽
I tried not to have that much emotional attachment to the game.
不要有太多情緒依戀
這是佛教吧？
That's Buddhism, right
“慈愛”是佛教用語
You know, and Metta's a Buddhist name.
我想盡量活在正面的環境裡
You wanna keep attaching yourself to as many positive things as possible.
回顧我的籃壇生涯
When you look at my career,
我不是好隊友，慈愛正好相反
not being a good teammate, like, Metta's the opposite.
它的意義是友誼、愛和關懷
Be a good friend, be love, and be kindness.
我想要和人溝通，想變得更好
I wanna communicate, I wanna be a better person. You know
這大概是慈愛的真諦
And that's pretty much what Metta means.
我不爽羅恩好多年
I had a real problem with Ron for years,
後來漸漸變成厭惡
and it grew a dislike in my system.
他奪冠時，也許變得更憤怒
I was probably even more angry once he won the championship.
羅恩亞泰斯特充分把握了第二次機會
[commentator] Ron Artest has made the most of his second chance.
從奧宮鬥毆事件開始，他一路奮鬥
And he's come all the way from that Palace brawl
最後和洛杉磯湖人隊拿下NBA冠軍
to NBA championship with the Los Angeles Lakers.
羅恩，湖人隊只有你
Ron, you're the only member of this Laker team
是第一次拿冠軍 拿到冠軍後，感覺怎麼樣？
to get that first championship.
You, my friend, are a champion. How does it feel
本來在印第安納時 我就該和傑曼、唐尼、賴瑞
I was supposed to get one with Jermaine and Donnie and Larry
賈馬爾汀斯利和傑夫福斯特拿到冠軍
and Jamaal Tinsley and Jeff Foster over there in Indiana,
我像懦夫一樣背棄了他們
and I bailed out on them. I feel like a coward.
我甚至不喜歡和他們共處一室 在他們面前，我就像個懦夫
I don't even like being in their presence. I feel like a coward in their presence,
因為我背棄了他們這些隊友
you know, 'cause I bailed out on them as a teammate.
現在我奪冠了，所以…
And then I get to get a championship, you know, so…
談談比賽吧
Let's talk about this game. You looked in the first half…
這件事我釋懷了 我損失很多錢，沒關係
I'm over the situation. I lost a lot of money. Whatever.
但傑曼好像還擺脫不了這個陰影
I still feel like Jermaine's being labeled by that.
傑曼歐尼爾
Jermaine O'Neal. [small laugh]
當時他快成為頂尖球員了
He was on the verge of becoming one of the greatest players ever. You know
看著今天的傑曼
[Walsh] When I look at Jermaine today,
我覺得他的損失可能最大
I thinkhe probably suffered more than all the players.
因為羅恩亞泰斯特最後加入湖人隊 拿到冠軍
Because Ronnie Artest ended up with the Lakers and won a championship.
連傑克都待過 聖安東尼奧這支冠軍球隊
Even Jack, who had played on a championship team, San Antonio.
傑曼的生涯提前中止
So Jermaine's career kinda got short-circuited.
事發當時，他要擔起當隊長的責任
The responsibility of carrying that team and being the leader was on him
但這不是他的錯
when all that happened, and it wasn't his fault.
卻成了代罪羔羊
But he got blamed for it.
[somber music playing]
我一直不想用“遺憾”這個字眼
I've never reallytried to use the word "regret,"
um,
但…
but…
它卻一直
it's a part of me
在…困擾著我
that, uh,
has always bothered me.
[somber music continues]
本台今天稍早在奧本山宮殿上方
Sky 4 was over the Palace of Auburn Hills earlier today,
工作人員開始拆除工程
where crews were beginning to demolish the place.
奧宮曾是底特律活塞隊的主場 他們在這裡拿過三屆NBA冠軍
[newswoman] The Palace was home to the Detroit Pistons
and saw three NBA championships
在2017年賽季後卻永久關閉
before it closed for good after the 2017 season.
這件事拖了好幾年
[O'Neal] This thing was drawn out for years.
[echoing commentator chatter]
我完全不想提起，我想往前走
[O'Neal] I didn't wanna talk to anybody. I wanted to move on with my life.
卻始終無法逃脫不了
I've never been able to get away from it though.
[uneasy music plays]
觀眾以為有票就能為所欲為
People thought that ticket guaranteed them to do whatever they wanted to do.
想怎麼做、怎麼對待人都可以
They can act and treat people any way they wanted.
[siren wails]
我沒說這樣多半是對的
[crowd yelling]
I'm not saying much of it was correct,
但觀眾對這些球員做了個人投資
but they hada personal investment in-in those ballplayers.
每年都會有人問我
[O'Neal] Pops up every single year.
連當時還沒出生的小孩都會問我
Kids that wasn't even born asking me about that.
球迷投入太多情感
[crowd yelling]
[Smith] Fans have such an emotional investment in it.
包括灰暗的情緒
There is a darkness there.
職業運動員不該衝進看臺
[commentator] If you're a professional athlete, you may not go into the stands.
天哪，浪費了好多可以用來調查
Boy, what a waste of a lot of time and resources
犯罪和謀殺案的時間和資源
when crimes and murders were taking place.
沒人關心誰打贏了刑事訴訟
Nobody cared about who won the criminal cases,
誰贏了上訴
who won the appeal case.
我有好幾年無法發聲
I wasn't able to speak for years.
這是我最後一次回答這些問題
This is the last fucking time you can ask me about this shit.
我不想聊丟啤酒杯的王八蛋
I don't wanna talk about that piece of shit motherfucker who threw that beer.
不想聊我的金錢損失
Okay I don't wanna talk about losing all that money no more.
太丟臉了
[commentator] This is a disgrace.
真要說起來，是我的錯 我以為這樣能贏球
If there's any fault, it's on me. I thought it would work.
我錯了
I wasn't right.
球迷和球員正在努力，球員…
[commentator] Fans and players are going at it. The players…
有些事永遠不會消失
Some things just never leave.
永遠不會消失
They never leave.
奧宮鬥毆事件就是一例
Malice in the Palace is… is one of those events.
也許到現在，還有一部分的我
There's a bit of me that probably to this very day
還留在拆除前的奧宮
is still in the Palace until they knock it down.
[somber music playing]
[explosion blasting]
[loud droning]
[somber droning plays]
[music fades]
字幕翻譯：易敬能